Guide to the Anne Gardner Edna St. Vincent Millay Collection, 1917-circa 1952
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Anne Gardner Edna St. Vincent Millay Collection,
1917-circa 1952
Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950
Gardner, Anne Wills (collector)
0.8 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, printed material, scrapbook documenting Anne Gardner's friendship with Edna St. Vincent Millay.
Biographical Note
Anne Wills Gardner graduated from Vassar College in 1917, along with the poet Edna St. Vincent Millay. During their years at Vassar, Gardner and Millay became friends and remained close until Millay's death in 1950.
Scope and Content Note
All material is from the personal Millay archive of Millay's close friend and Vassar classmate, Anne Wills Gardner. Highlights include a long letter from Millay while traveling in Vienna; a studio portrait of Millay taken by Marcia Stein, a noted Broadway portraitist of the 1910s and 1920s; and a customized large red binder stamped in gold "Selected Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay" with several typed poems inscribed by Millay to Gardner.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Edna St. Vincent Millay Papers
John S. Van E. Kohn Edna St. Vincent Millay Collection
Names:
Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Subject Headings
Subjects:
American poetry--20th century--Women authors; Poets, American--20th century; Women authors, American--20th century
VCL Categories:
Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, May 2020. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, January 2024.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Jett Whitehead, 2017. [M2017-007]
Series List
- Series I. POEMS OF MILLAY, circa 1916-1917
  This series consists of typescripts of Millay's poems, some with annotation sin her hand, and a binder of typscripts entitled Selected Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay.
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE FROM MILLAY, 1917-1933
  This series consists of letters from Millay to Anne Garder.
- Series III. PRINTED MATERIALS, 1917-1952
  This series consists of copies of magazines in which appeared poems by Millay.
- Series IV. PHOTOGRAPHS, circa 1920-1948
  This series consists of photographs, icluding a studio portrait of Millay taken by noted Broadway portraitist, Marcia Stein.
- Series V. SCRAPBOOK AND NOTES, undated
  This series consists of a scrapbook kept by Anne Garnder, as well as notes for Anne Gardner McNeile's planned biograph of Millay.
Container List
- Series I. Poems of Millay
  - "Five Limericks in Love of Anne,", undated (Folder 1.1)
  - "To Anne,", undated (Folder 1.2)
  - "Possession,", undated; (typed and handwritten, with annotations in Millay's hand) (Folder 1.3)
  - "Departure,", undated (Folder 1.4)
  - 2 Sonnets, undated (Folder 1.5)
  - "For One Lancelot,", undated (Folder 1.6)
  - "A Visit to the Asylum,", undated (Folder 1.7)
  - "Travel,", undated (Folder 1.8)
  - Untitled, undated (Folder 1.9)
  - "To Love Impuissant" and "The Faithful Lover,", undated (Folder 1.10)
  - "Omnia Bella Devoratis,", undated (Folder 1.11)
  - "Interlude,", undated (Folder 1.12)
  - Selected Poems of Edna St. Vincent Millay, 1916 (Folder 2.3 (Oversize))
- Series II. Correspondence from Millay
  - Letter, 1917 October 31 (Folder 1.13)
  - Letter, 1919 December 22 (Folder 1.14)
  - Letter with transcription, 1921 December 23 (Folder 1.15)
  - Letter, 1923 November 20 (Folder 1.16)
  - Letter, 1925 August 23 (Folder 1.17)
  - Letter, 1925 September 23 (Folder 1.18)
  - Letter, 1927 December 6 (Folder 1.19)
  - Letter, 1928 November 15 (Folder 1.20)
  - Letter, 1930 July 14 (Folder 1.21)
  - Letter, 1931 February 25 (Folder 1.22)
  - Cable, 1933 March 25 (Folder 1.23)
- Series III. Printed Materials
  - "The Wall of Dominoes," Vassar Miscellany Monthly, 1917 May (Folder 1.24)
  - "Edna St. Vincent Millay – A Mountain Portrait," Vanity Fair, 1927 May (Folder 2.2 (Oversize))
  - "Fear," The Outlook, 1927 November (Folder 1.25)
  - "Edna St. Vincent Millay: A Memoir," The Nation, 1952 April (Folder 1.26)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Portrait of Millay, 1920 September (Folder 2.1 (Oversize))
  - Millay and Eugene at Steepletop, 1948 (Folder 1.27)
  - Portrait of Millay, undated (Folder 1.28)
  - Portrait of Millay, undated (Folder 1.29)
  - Portrait of Millay, undated (Folder 1.30)
  - Photograph, undated (Folder 1.31)
- Series V. Scrapbook and Notes
  - Scrapbook about Millay, undated (Folder 2.4 (Oversize))
  - Anne Gardner McNeile's notes for a biography of Millay, undated (Folder 1.32)